<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix id="scintilla">
  <title>Using Scintilla with FXRuby</title>

  <simplesect>
    <title>What is Scintilla?</title>

    <para><ulink url="http://www.scintilla.org">Scintilla</ulink> is a free
    source code editing component developed by Neil Hodgson for the Win32 and
    GTK+ platforms.</para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>What is FXScintilla?</title>

    <para><ulink
    url="http://savannah.gnu.org/projects/fxscintilla">FXScintilla </ulink> is
    a FOX widget that wraps around the Scintilla component, or, if you wish,
    the FOX "port" of Scintilla. Until recently it was developed by Gilles Filippini,
    and as of this writing the latest release is available for download from
    <ulink
    url="http://download.savannah.gnu.org/releases/fxscintilla/fxscintilla-1.71.tar.gz">http://download.savannah.gnu.org/releases/fxscintilla/fxscintilla-1.71.tar.gz</ulink>.</para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Compiling FXScintilla</title>

    <para>The FXScintilla distribution contains everything you need to build
    the FXScintilla widget and begin using it in your C++-based FOX
    applications. That is to say, you do not have to separately download the
    Scintilla source code from the Scintilla home page. When you unpack the
    FXScintilla tarball, you should get a new <filename class="directory">
    fxscintilla-1.71</filename> directory containing the source code for the
    FOX port of the Scintilla widget.</para>

    <para>As of the 1.46 release of FXScintilla, the build process has been
    "autoconfiscated" and should seem very familiar to you if you've built
    other open-source software (like FOX) from the source code. The
    <filename>INSTALL</filename> file in the top-level directory should
    provide enough instruction for you to build and install FXScintilla for
    either Unix or Microsoft Windows.</para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Enabling FXScintilla Support in FXRuby</title>

    <para>The next step is to build a version of FXRuby (from its source code)
    with the optional FXScintilla support enabled. If you're working on a Unix
    or Linux system and have installed FXScintilla in one of the standard
    installation directories (e.g. under <filename
    class="directory">/usr/include</filename> or <filename
    class="directory">/usr/local/include</filename>), the regular FXRuby build
    process should automatically detect it and enable FXScintilla
    support.</para>

    <para>If you have installed FXScintilla in some non-standard place, or if
    you're building the code on Microsoft Windows, you will need to specify a
    few additional configuration options at the beginning.</para>

    <para>You can configure the build on Unix or Linux systems by
    typing:</para>

    <screen>
$ <command>sudo gem install fxruby-1.6.7.gem --force -- --with-fxscintilla-include=/usr/local/include/fxscintilla --with-fxscintilla-lib=/usr/local/lib</command>
</screen>

    <para>or, when compiling with Microsoft Visual C++, by typing:</para>

    <screen>
C:\&gt; <command>gem install fxruby-1.6.7.gem --force -- --with-fox-include=C:\fox-1.6.25\include --with-fox-lib=C:\fox-1.6.25\lib --with-fxscintilla-include=C:\fxscintilla-1.71\include --with-fxscintilla-lib=C:\fxscintilla-1.71\lib</command>
</screen>

    <para>Past this point, the build and installation process for either
    platform should be the same as for standard builds. To test your new
    FXScintilla-enabled build of FXRuby, try running the
    <filename>scintilla-test.rb</filename> example program in the FXRuby
    <filename class="directory">examples</filename> subdirectory.</para>
  </simplesect>
</appendix>
