<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="gems">
  <title>Installing from Gems</title>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>FXRuby uses <ulink
    url="http://rubygems.rubyforge.org">RubyGems</ulink> as its preferred
    packaging and distribution method. The code is available both as</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>a "source" gem, which contains source code that must be compiled
        on your computer before it's installed; and,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a "binary" gem, which contains a precompiled version of the code
        for a specific operating system (such as Windows).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Installing from a Source Gem</title>

    <para>If you've already downloaded the source gem, you can install it by
    typing:</para>

    <screen>$ <command>sudo gem install fxruby-1.6.13.gem</command></screen>

    <para>Note the use of the <command>sudo</command> command to invoke
    superuser privileges, since you'll typically need superuser privileges to
    install the library files. By default, the source gem will look for your
    FOX (and optionally, FXScintilla) installation in a few standard places,
    such as the <filename>/usr</filename>, <filename>/usr/local</filename> and
    <filename>/sw</filename> directories. If you've installed those libraries
    under some other directory (for example, in your home directory) you might
    need to pass some additional arguments on the command line, e.g.</para>

    <screen>$ <command>sudo gem install fxruby-1.6.13.gem --force -- --with-fox-include=/home/lyle/include/fox-1.6 --with-fox-lib=/home/lyle/lib</command></screen>

    <para>If you're installing a source gem on a Windows box, you'd instead
    type something like:</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt; <command>gem install fxruby-1.6.13.gem --force -- --with-fox-include=C:\include\fox-1.6 --with-fox-lib=C:\lib</command></screen>

    <para>If you're installing a source gem, it can take quite awhile to build
    FXRuby, so this might be a good time to take a coffee break. You won't see
    any compiler output appear on the screen while the gem is compiling, but
    rest assured that the output is being saved into the
    <filename>gem_make.out</filename> file.</para>

    <para>As a quick sanity check, to make sure that all is well, you should
    probably fire up <filename>irb</filename> and try to require the FXRuby
    gem once the installation is complete:</para>

    <screen>$ <command>irb</command>
irb(main):001:0&gt; <userinput><command>require 'rubygems'</command></userinput>
true
irb(main):002:0&gt; <command>require 'fox16'</command>
true</screen>

    <para>If the import failed (usually with a message along the lines of
    "Cannot load library"), first check the "Things That Can Go Wrong" section
    of this chapter. If that doesn't help, drop me an e-mail or ask around on
    the Ruby newsgroup or mailing list; it's quite likely that someone else
    has run into this problem too. Once you do have a working FXRuby
    installation, you're ready to check out the example programs.</para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Installing from a Binary Gem</title>

    <para>To install a binary gem for Windows, just type:</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt; <command>gem install fxruby-1.6.13-mswin32.gem</command></screen>

    <para>As a quick sanity check, to make sure that all is well, you should
    probably fire up <filename>irb</filename> and try to require the FXRuby
    gem once the installation is complete:</para>

    <screen>C:\&gt; <command>irb</command>
irb(main):001:0&gt; <userinput><command>require 'rubygems'</command></userinput>
true
irb(main):002:0&gt; <command>require 'fox16'</command>
true</screen>

    <para>If the import failed (usually with a message along the lines of
    "Cannot load library"), first check the "Things That Can Go Wrong" section
    of this chapter. If that doesn't help, drop me an e-mail or ask around on
    the Ruby newsgroup or mailing list; it's quite likely that someone else
    has run into this problem too. Once you do have a working FXRuby
    installation, you're ready to check out the example programs.</para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Things That Can Go Wrong</title>

    <para><emphasis>"Cannot load library"</emphasis></para>

    <para>On Linux and other Unix systems that support shared libraries, FOX
    is typically installed as a shared library named
    <filename>libFOX-1.6.so</filename>. After all of the source files for
    FXRuby are compiled, the last step is to link all of the FXRuby object
    files together with the FOX library (and possibly other system libraries)
    to produce a new shared object that Ruby can import as an extension
    module.</para>

    <para>There are a few things that can go wrong when you try to import this
    extension into Ruby. A common problem is that the operating system cannot
    locate the FOX shared library (<filename>libFOX-1.6.so</filename>) when it
    tries to dynamically load the FXRuby extension module; when this happens,
    the error message will look something like:</para>

    <screen>$ <command>irb</command>
irb(main):001:0&gt; <userinput>require 'fox16'</userinput>
LoadError: libFOX-1.6.so: cannot open shared object file: No such file or directory - /usr/local/lib/ruby/1.8/i686-linux/fox16.so
        from (irb):1:in 'require'
        from (irb):1
    </screen>

    <para>Note that the wording of this error message may be slightly
    different, depending on your operating environment. One workaround for
    this problem is to modify the <constant>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</constant>
    environment variable to include the directory where
    <filename>libFOX-1.6.so</filename> is installed. For example, if
    <filename>libFOX-1.6.so</filename> is installed in <filename
    class="directory">/usr/local/lib</filename>, try setting:</para>

    <screen>$ <command>export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/usr/local/lib</command>
$ <command>irb</command>
irb(main):001:0&gt; <userinput>require 'fox16'</userinput>
</screen>

    <para>If this works, you can of course permanently add the
    <constant>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</constant> setting to your login file(s) so that
    you don't have to remember to type it each time. Another approach that
    should work for Linux is to modify your
    <filename>/etc/ld.so.conf</filename> file to include the installation
    directory (e.g. <filename>/usr/local/lib</filename>). If you'd like to do
    this instead, you'll need to (as root):</para>

    <orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>Edit your <filename>/etc/ld.so.conf</filename> file and add the
        directory where <filename>libFOX-1.6.so</filename> is installed;
        and,</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>At the shell prompt, type <command>ldconfig</command> to reload
        the linker configuration.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </simplesect>
</chapter>